So. Yes.
Hello everyone and welcome.
I'm Kavisha Alagiya, and for the next 60 minutes or so.
We are going on a journey
into invisible spaces.
We are going to look for the hidden
mathematical dimensions
where your words or our words live.
When we write for AI or LMS.
This workshop is called Exile
to Latent Space.
Writing from dimensions
we cannot enter and.
Let me start with a bold claim.
When we write with or for large language
models, our words
undergo radical transformation
and they are translated into vectors.
What I came to know and disturb
and distributed across
high dimensional spaces
inaccessible to human perception
like it is incomprehensible
to know each and everything behind
the workings, behind the behind
the algorithms and everything.
So today we are going to explore what
that actually means and white matters.
So before we begin,
just let me know if you have any questions
or anything else
to know while we are exploring.
So yes,
it is going to be a poet inquiry
to understand what is latent space.
Where do our words go?
We are going to experience and explore
the word embeddings.
It is known as vector embeddings.
See hidden structures,
how the words are operating and what large
language language models are giving us
as a form of answer to our prompts.
And we are also going to reflect
what does this mean for writing?
Who controls the spaces and how they are
answering to us, how they are reflected.
So let us come together to discuss
what this means for writing
and who controls the spaces.
What are the politics
of latent representation?
What does it mean
that we are structurally, structurally
excluded
from where our own words that preceded?
So first let me ask you a question.
When you write.
When you write with or for AI,
where do your words go
and what happens there?
That is our central mystery.
When you write for AI, what happens the.
What?
What are the current happenings
which you might have?
Can anybody answer?
Would you like
verbal answers or in the chat answers?
Yes. What would be good?
Okay, well,
I assume that when I type something
into a large language model
that it becomes absorbed
and part of the training data, and
I don't know what happens from there.
Yes, that is exactly at inquiry.
So what happens in between the words
we feed in or the prompts we give
and the answer we are given back.
So most of us have no idea.
And it's a mystery.
And here's the thing.
It's not accidentally mysterious.
It's structurally,
structurally inaccessible.
And that is why we are naming
that as latent
the space where our words are transformed
or exist in mathematical dimensions we
literally cannot perceive or comprehend.
Or that is why
we are investigating this today.
And I'm going to show you
as much as possible
what the invisible spaces look like. So.
The research which
was done before on neural embeddings shows
that meaning in AI systems is organized
through statistical proximity
rather than narrative sequence
or authorial intention.
If we if we communicate with large
language models and we want our intention
to be catered in our, in the,
in the, in our answers or in the answers
which this large language
models are giving us,
they're there, this, this intention,
the context.
Or we would say human interactions
are compromised basically.
So traditional writing, if we put
the word exile then it is transformed.
When it goes to AI, it is transformed
in numerical binary digits.
Words.
Here in traditional method,
words are perceived as meanings.
Here. What's become coordinates?
There is this human intention
in our traditional methods, whereas
when it when it is transformed in AI,
it becomes statistical patterns.
And whatever we are being fed
or we are being given is
300 plus dimension spaces.
That is this mathematical space.
We human I can perceive two three
dimensions, page screen things.
So what is this latent space?
Latent space is the hidden high
dimensional mathematical environment
where AI organizes its meaning.
Words
as meaning becomes words as ordinates.
And that is all we have seen.
So this the characteristics are 300
plus dimensions.
Human can only visualize three,
whereas here there are 300 plus dimensions
which our brains are literally
cannot construct a mental image of 300
dimensional space.
It is mathematically inaccessible
and hidden from direct human perception.
It relies on statistical organization
structured by word co-occurrence patterns.
And here's where our theme is centralized
unsupervised learning created
automatically through training.
As we know, large language
models are learning from our prompts
and they are developing itself with that.
It is an environment where we only see
outputs, not the space itself.
So here is like Layer
and Joanna emphasize latent space
is not merely a technical substrate
but an emerging esthetic environment.
It produces meaning through aggregation
and learned association
rather than direct representation.
And as you, as we the writer, are excluded
from this thing, the
we are excluded.
So we are curious
where this aggregation happens.
So I had given the exiled metaphor.
We are exiled from the things we want.
Our intentions.
So the traditional authorship
in traditional authorship
and author chooses words with intention
that the text then
reaches, reaches to the reader
and the flow is very clear.
Whereas if we look
look at the latent space writing,
the author still provides words.
But then those words enter the AI system.
And here's the key part.
The transformation occurs in hidden space.
Your words are converted
into vectors and navigated.
According to the.
Associations or the structured, or in a
in a very transformative space.
The things that are happening.
This is this is the exile
which I'm talking about.
So writers contribute expression
while remaining structurally excluded
from the spaces
where the expression is reorganized.
And there comes the entire
historical context
of direct authorship,
procedural authorship, and latent space.
So in direct authorship
there is most of human history.
The author has full authorial control over
the message and form seeing in writers
like Homer Woods, Virginia Woolf,
and the model is very simple.
Author gives the text to the reader.
And this is how the leadership has been
since then.
Procedural in proceed.
When it comes to procedural, this involves
surrendering direct control to rules
and systems. For example, group there.
There was this.
Absence
of the letter E in the entire poem.
Or foreign literature
and the cut ups writings which are
which were there cutting the newspaper
or cutting the text,
and then merging it
and creating a poetry.
And then that comes algo.
Ergodic literature, espionage,
organic literature,
concept of organic literature,
which for foreground writing
that writing is shaped by structures
and reader cannot fully survey.
So latent space writing intensifies
this condition.
The writer composes for hidden geometries
whose logics must be inferred
through output alone.
Word embedding.
Visualization.
So now we are going to have a live
demonstration.
We are getting to the project TensorFlow.
I hope my screen is visible.
The next step.
Projector TensorFlow org.
Here we are given.
What we are looking at is a dimensional,
simplified version
of that three 300 dimensional space.
This tool makes in invisible
statistical relationships
visible like we can see.
Let me
show you another way how to explore.
I'm going to ask this.
The coordinates
which you will will be able to see here.
There is one line.
And this is how the words
are clustered in vector embeddings.
And we can come to know if I just click
put a cursor on indirectly,
then I can relate.
How many words are there
clustered in that parts
of your prevailing services?
Word marking perspectives.
So the entire thing,
the entire thing to understand
here is that words are grouped.
For example, busy spirits pace.
They are synonyms.
Twitter guided speaker, terrible charity,
atheism.
Gnostic roots.
Descendent
and roots
are somewhat relatable to each other.
So this is how the entire space
looks like.
This is how I work.
If I search here. Excite.
Retirement.
List.
You can go to this project dot TensorFlow.
I'm putting this link here.
And also explore how, how,
how or what words are semantically
between home and exile,
jail place, retirement, hiding and exile.
And simultaneously,
if we want to experiment this thing,
we can ask
GPT to provide.
How?
What words are semantically.
And it will provide us
how how these things are working
displacement, relocation,
settlement management, migration return.
So in this embedding project,
you will be able to see how things
how the words
are grouped at one space.
For example.
Exploitation purchase company supplied.
So these are all economical terms
extending
recommendations memes
psychiatric.
Then here there is the stress
professional stages
managers constructed Stem numbers.
So this words are in
a way grouped in that manner.
Yes it will be.
Now your turn.
I am putting an effort.
How how do you think you can write in
in the chat box?
How do you think of.
I am giving you some some time
to do the visual exploration.
Go to project or TensorFlow and load
the word to all data set.
Here it is.
But to wake
10-K dataset and
search for the word
important to your writing and observe how.
Observe its neighboring words in 3D space.
The entire semantic
view. Yes.
Great media.
Apps train is not not in data set.
Fine.
So we can go to again
and ask what words
are systematically.
Similar.
Media.
Platform.
Career.
Magazines,
broadcast newspaper, TV creative critics.
Okay, fine.
So what neighbors appear?
What surprises?
What's missing that we can find?
What what does this reveal?
So this this through this thing
we can actually understand.
The the relationships,
the statistical relationships
we can actually observe
which is made visible.
The semantic clustering,
similar meanings cluster together
a simplified shade of three and 300
dimensional space. So.
Exploring the the TensorFlow platform
give us how the words are organized.
If asked if we ask what words
are semantically similar to the word
which you have used media for example,
what concepts like between what A and B
exile and home are and by taking notes,
what are the neighbor words?
What surprises? What's missing?
What does this reveal?
We can we can actually understand
how the how the systems are working.
What is the latent space? How how.
Plane exercises targeted?
Oxford observes.
Want to go a deeper?
Logos readings test
circle logos, logos.
Markers.
Makers or makers?
Literature.
Words.
Reading.
Reading was somewhere here.
So this this is how we can know the
the workings behind things.
So yes,
for philosophical inquiries
into latent spaces, frequency
versus resonance, what does it mean
that AI organizes our words
based on statistical frequency
rather than poetic resonance?
Like, for example,
I want to make my intention visible
on the on on writings of AI.
Then I would obviously have to first
observe how,
how how words that in a way catered.
And by this things
I can understand
that there is the statistical frequencies.
They are statistically organized.
They are semantically organized
based on their meanings.
Who decides who decides how meaning
is organized in this invisible place,
in this invisible,
mathematically complicated spaces?
And there is this inaccessible spaces.
If you cannot access the space
where your words are transformed,
what does this mean for authorship?
The critical questions which are the
politics behind these things?
The the question of ownership is this
whatever I am asking to large language
models to cater me based on my prompts
so that writing, when it emerges,
it is transformed, obviously,
and from the depths of latent spaces.
I cannot say whether it is my writing,
because if my intention is something else
and it is getting me a very beautiful
and esthetics
enriching content,
but still the intention is not,
I would not be able to provide
justice to it
when it comes to intention,
authorial intention and everything.
So these are the questions
which can be posed so unsupervised
that politics is about this how patterns
form AI discovers structures on its own.
No explicit human labels
are there patterns from billions of texts
and codes,
existing biases from training data.
And there is this, again,
entire OPEC organization
because it is unsupervised when it comes
to supervision and fine tuning
how outputs are controlled human label,
whether it's a good or bad that.
Is this a feature available?
You can mark it whether you
like the response or you don't like.
So so and again
this corporate values are enforced.
When it comes to
if I, if my intention is to generate
a poem which, which will in a way
lead to certain.
Wordings
which are not acceptable
for this large language model.
So again corporate values are enforced
where they are
not supposed to cater these things.
And it will report me
as an inappropriate content
or anything like that and decides
what's appropriate or not.
So this large language
models are controlled
when it comes to supervision,
and it would decide by itself
whether it's appropriate
whether to cater the needs to of the
of the prompt writer or not.
And it restricts certain creative outputs.
So again there is this opaque criteria.
How how.
Things are working.
Like if I want to give it
a prompt of a doctor
or an engineer,
write a story around a doctor or engineer.
Again
there will be output a 75% or so output
where the doctor or engineer would be
male.
So we can also observe
gender biases in this.
And underneath
that that there is this training data,
which text where,
which language would dominate,
which which gender would dominate,
which voices will be at the center
and what what are in the margins.
So this data encodes are in a way
when it comes to supervision,
they become bias,
in terms of gender associations
or cultural assumptions
or dominant produce.
So finally supervision dictates
what is deemed appropriate
and who makes those goals which which can
ultimately restrict creative expression.
So when it comes to literary
and a large language models so that there
we can find a certain kind of control
and where the spaces are not neutral and
whose patterns whose value.
So what's encoded in latent space,
visible layer.
What we see is, is AI generated text.
While from from inside
or from the the very interior
essence is lying on the training data.
Which texts were included?
Which language dominate?
Voices are centered encoded bias
encoded bias is obviously
and supervision what deemed appropriate,
who makes those calls?
What creative expressions are restricted?
This has also been observed
that literature
now operates
within latent spaces that are opaque
and only partially interpreted
interpretable.
So that was also one of the observations
that was made. And.
So where do we go from here.
So the experiment was done.
And keep keep exploring visualization
tools.
Try adversarial
prompting and create with or against AI.
Once once you will ask 100 times to AI
or even ten times it will change.
So of hills.
My mother was a computer science
AI, art man, artificial esthetics.
Through this
we can come to know that writing
right from this Excel or.
Who control the spaces is
the main thing creating.
Control, advocating, advocate for transfer
transparency or demand accountability
like we are supposed to train our models.
That is how we can come to a conclusion.
So if latent space is where
meaning now lives
and we cannot enter it,
what new forms of writing
might emerge from negotiation,
from negotiating this exile?
So again, we can interpret
or take an inference that
by continuously modifying
or asking questions
or or continuously
researching on things,
how how it how it
how the things are relating,
we can create a much beautiful
or statics out outputs from this.
So here are the references and the tools.
We in a way explored where this.
Yes. Hello.
We are still here.
Yeah.
So this was the thing from my side and I.
Apologize
if I have not provided justice to things,
but I tried.
Oh no, that was that was just wonderful.
Thank you so much.
I personally picked up
some really interesting stuff
when I plugged in some keywords.
Would anyone else like to share
some observations of what they found,
or would you like us to move
into a discussion?
Yes, that would be great.
I would love to listen to the inputs.
Okay.
Would anyone like to share?
This would have interesting if
if audience would have participated.
Oh it's okay, I think.
I think we can find
some audience participation in it.
Looks like
Joanna has something to share. Yes.
Thank you.
You know, I have a question that's.
It's related to my own work, but
I'm partial of possibilities
in this project
of visualize, you know,
you know, kind of visualizing AI, right.
Visualizing generative text production
is, is illustrating and informing others
about how these systems
work part of your project,
and if so, how are you documenting that?
This this
has came from curious,
from my curiosity,
like how this models are working,
because algorithms are in a way becoming
more personal and they are learning
the the individuals individually.
So I was I was explaining to this thing
to my students, whether
like they are literature students
and they are
they were supposed to write
a mediated poetry, AI person,
human mediated poetry, and they come up
with very, very beautiful poems.
Now, the thing was that this,
this generated
the curiosity of
how things are going to be in
future, like how want to create
what would be the authors,
who would be the author,
who would consider as the final author,
who the the human
who gave the prompt, or the machine
who created based on that prompt.
So, so this created so
we are in a process
of documenting all such things.
And if we are going to document
this thing, then again
the citation, the problem
we will be facing here because these are
these are a workable things
and a very practical,
sites and everything.
So that can not be in a way
documented traditionally.
And if we have the entire new poetics
to analyze this digital literature
and electronic literature
as compared to traditional
literature or print literature,
then we would obviously require
new methods of citation to to document
and to preserve the things
we have.
The entire new poetics, digital poetics,
when it comes to analyzing
digital literature.
So we will most probably
I think we will need digital methods,
digital citation methods, wherein
we can document
the screen recording while we are working,
how the things are, in a way
coming to conclusion.
And yes, that that is one way.
Thank you.
I hope I am able to answer.
Did you have the chat open?
I think people were posting screenshots
of things they were finding in the
the latent space.
Angela was looking for Latina,
which wasn't there in the dataset,
but Latino was and
chiffon
had was looking at the word cult.
There's some Siobhan put racist in
with the maxed out neighbors there,
I think there there's some really.
It's really fun to explore this,
which is cool.
And it makes me wonder
about how this like,
oh, V has colonialism.
It's interesting to think about,
like how this data set might change is
or if this set would change over time.
Like as we continue
to use language and words differently, or
as meanings of words change amid cultures
like the differences between,
you know, like this 2026 moment
and in ten years, whether these words
will be similarly associated.
I'm sure many of them would be able
to be interesting to see, like where,
if anything, like, you know,
like like constellations over time,
like drift
just a tiny bit like imperceptibly.
Yes. It would be very interesting
to observe how how things, things
these things will progress in future
because there were certain
there will be certain words
which will be absent in this.
And you will find 2 to 3 words,
same words in the entire clusters.
There are cultural languages
not assessed or represented.
One can dive deeper into dialects
and indigenous languages.
I was exploring this,
but I don't know how to create this thing.
The word embeddings.
Indigenous?
Yes, that would be really cool, even for
like over the course of a single authors.
The way that certain words are associated
within an author's work compared to
I don't know if there's a ways to
to create those clusters for other corpus
or something like that.
I am not sure how that works.
It would be great in a way,
if if people are able
to create these things.
Basically, I have been shirking
my moderator responsibilities
because I've been playing with the thing.
So, but all right, let me see
if there's anything else here in the chat
for us as well.
Angelica
is also very interested
in exploring this. Yes.
I also just plugged in the word
indigenous,
and I'm interested in some of the cluster
kind of pieces that come up near it.
You know, we have things like Aboriginal
is in their Hawaiian
dramatic, Ethiopia.
And then also I'm
seeing minority and minorities.
So that's fun.
All right.
You know,
so we can see in that image as well
we can see biases against communities.
Yes. Yes.
Because if
I'm wrong, I know you talked about this,
but this sample, this
this sample of words is a like
the 10,000 most common words.
Yes, yes, yes.
Basically working on the inputs
which people give time and again.
And that is how it is forming
a pattern, a patterned
system. Yes.
It would provide a new word.
Mexican.
Is it describing a group or language.
How is it defining within latency
is another point of research.
This is exciting to me.
Sorry.
Very good question.
That is also.
Yeah. I'm sorry.
I was wondering how you like,
experienced this interface
and this data set
and like exploring with this
as a creative practice,
like if how would you translate this
sort of like cluster for into like,
like writing prompts or projects or
like how do you, how do you want
to work with this creatively?
This was
one my very first experience,
and I was quite nervous about that thing
because the attending yellow
for the first time and that to going
beyond my my comfort zone.
I am a person of literature and
I was working with this things and this.
This in a way started as I explained,
this started in classroom
back then when students came up with
with very creative outputs.
But the pattern was same.
So that developed the curiosity,
how these things are working,
what is behind it,
and if in future I have to
I have to work with this,
then it is obviously a very, very
good idea.
I would say an excellent idea.
And what was your
second query again, please?
Let me see.
I was going to hold on.
I will follow up with you
in just a second.
I need to look back at my notes.
Yeah.
Exactly.
It's a very funny, fun, fun
learning thing.
The, the abstract that you
that I was looking at for
this panel is like, would you want us
to write experimental texts
responding to linguistic exile?
And so I was wondering,
like if you had any, like,
writing prompts or something, or like,
how do you want us to engage with that
if we're going to do something creative
along those lines?
If we want to be creative
with this experiment, how can we be?
Yes.
We we are supposed to ask everything
to large
language models
whenever we come across this thing,
this type of things,
because it it will be only the, the true
medium to get our answers.
Because again
this this vector embeddings are designed
by that that language models
based on that language models only.
So Okay.
Will you please. I'm sorry.
No, that makes sense.
There's like
a, like a cool creative practice in
interacting with the large language model
and seeing what comes out, and then maybe
like reworking with that language.
And like numerous times
we are supposed to work with that
and that is how it will improve.
Thank you so much.
So if there are any observations
or any anything.
All right.
Do we have any further questions or
anything someone else would like to share?
We could end early if we need to.
Thank you so much, everyone.
Yes, this is very interesting and I
very intrigued already by just what
we've been able
to pull up in this time
from my poles for colonialism.
And Japan were very telling.
And then I see I'm really intrigued
by what Anjali pulled up
with Latino
being in the data set, but not Latina.
And we have it seems like
we have a lot to work with here.
Thank you.
And we are coming up
on a lunch break here.
So at least here in eastern
time, folks are encouraged to stretch,
step away from their computers,
reset your gaze no matter where you are.
But after the break, you will have our
keynote from the Flores
on impossible beyond impossible writing.
Nicely.
And then we'll have a paper session
and a panel
going on in the 2:00 block
before we go into our final events.
The town Hall, where we'll be making
the announcement about 2027
conference, and our award ceremony,
where we will be
celebrating folks
from within the community.
So please consider joining us
for some of the rest of your Saturday.
And thank you all, especially thank you
for that intriguing workshop
and new tools and ways of thinking
about text to play with going forward.
And.